Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Moving Images Collection FILMS.001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I. Transport Workers Union of America Films, 1930-1977; 34.5 Linear Feet in 16 record cartons and 177 film cans; 13.3 Gigabytes in 18 digital files
  - Subseries I.A. Films, 1930-1977
    - Bus Footage, 1941 (Film canister c6, 16mm film reels 001_0892)
      Bus driving, bus passengers, and traffic in New York City.
    - Demonstration, circa 1941 (Box 16, Film canister c4, 16mm film reels 001_0384)
      Transport Workers Union members picket the homes of more than a dozen individual TWU members (in different Manhattan locations and other boroughs) who have "deserted" the union; Michael Quill and other union leaders are shown speaking at outdoor rallies.
    - United We Are Invincible, 1941
      A documentary telling the story of the Transport Workers Union's successful March 1941 strike against the New York City Omnibus Corporation and Fifth Avenue Coach Company.
      - Complete film with additional sequence (Box 22, 16mm film reels 001_0898)
        This roll contains two unrelated sequences: The first is a short (2-minute) faded color sequence with shots of a propeller airplane, maintenance workers working on airplanes outdoors and inside a hangar, baggage handlers loading luggage, and a flight crew. The second is the complete film United We Are Invincible.
      - Film excerpt (Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0215)
      - Trims (Film canister c241, 16mm film reels 001_0771)
      - Trims (Box 18, Film canister c78, 16mm film reels 001_0358)
        See the video reproduction cuid37010 in Subseries I.B.
        Sequences and outtakes from the documentary. Includes footage of strikers and TWU leaders at rallies and demonstrations.
    - CIO Convention, circa 1943 (Film canister c6, 16mm film reels 001_0893)
    - Parades -- May Day circa 1946, Labor Day 1961, 1946-1961 (Film canister c104, 16mm film reels 001_0279)
      The first sequence is May Day, 1946 or, 1947; the second sequence is Labor Day, 1961.
    - May Day 1948, Union Voice Local 65, 13 Astor Place, May, 1948 (Film canister c104, 16mm film reels 001_0277)
      May Day rally and demonstration. Includes shots of a young Pete Seeger performing.
    - Sixth Biennial Convention, December, 1948
      - Film (Film canister c6, 16mm film reels 001_0889, 001_0890)
      - Film (Box 17, Film canister c7, 16mm film reels 001_0378)
        See the video reproduction cuid36983 in Subseries I.B.
      - Film (Box 17, Film canister c7, 16mm film reels 001_0377)
      - Film (Film canister c157, 16mm film reels 001_0345, 001_0346)
    - Seventh Biennial Convention Highlights, December 6-9, 1950 (Film canister c9, 16mm film reels 001_0798)
      See the video reproduction cuid36985 in Subseries I.B.
      Highlights of the Transport Workers Union's Seventh Biennial Convention, held at the union's Transport Hall.
    - Americans at Work, circa 1950s (Box 29, 16mm film reels 001_0267)
      This film is part of a film series produced for the AFL-CIO. It focuses on subway workers (represented by the Transport Workers Union) in New York City and the New York City subway system, giving an overview of different jobs and functions. Music and voice-over narrate the footage.
    - The Amsterdam News Debutante Ball, circa 1950s (Film canister c127, 16mm film reels 001_0272)
      Footage depicts a dance or debutante ball for young black women. A banner in the background reads: "The Amsterdam News Welcomes You." Various other banners around the large room have state names, including New Jersey and Tennessee, perhaps indicating that this is a national event.
    - Arthur Goldberg Statement, circa 1950s (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0847)
      See the video reproduction cuid1028 in Subseries I.B.
      Statement for Transport Workers Union delivered by Arthur Goldberg, union's Special Counsel (later U.S. Supreme Court Justice).
    - Bus Clips, circa 1950s (Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0855)
      Buses and passengers in mid-town Manhattan.
    - Bus Strike Announcement, circa 1950s (Film canister c46, 16mm film reels 001_0824)
      Michael Quill announces that a bus strike has been called off.
    - Bus Strike Trims, circa 1950s (Film canister c170, 16mm film reels 001_0196)
      Miscellaneous trims, many of which relate to Transport Workers Union's 1953 strike against New York City's private bus lines.
    - Contract Negotiations, circa 1950s (Film canister c119, 16mm film reels 001_0248)
      Transport Workers Union's officers stating some of union's contract demands in what appears to be negotiations with employer.
    - Furniture Workers Minter, circa 1950s (Film canister c127, 16mm film reels 001_0269, 001_0270, 001_0271, Box 23, 16mm film reels 001_0850)
      Trims -- A labor union (possibly the Furniture Workers' Union) banquet, dance, and award ceremonies.
    - Industrial Machinery Trims, circa 1950s (Film canister c198, 35mm film reels 001_0177)
      Miscellaneous trims, mostly of workers using industrial machinery. Most are from longer sequences present elsewhere in the Collection. Only sequence that does not appear to be duplicated elsewhere in the Collection is (4-:03:02 - 4-:03:34) Wide-angle shot of workers at powerhouse raising and lowering a large engine block.
    - Joseph Curran on Meet the Press, circa 1950s (Film canister c223, 16mm film reels 001_0765)
      Interview with Joseph Curran of the National Maritime Union on a program in the "Meet the Press" series broadcast on NBC. The reporters focus on Curran's position on the AFL-CIO resolution to cut ties with the International Brotherhood of Teamsters and International Longshoremen's Association, and his involvement in organizing a "Transportation Conference" on the waterfront that includes his union, the Teamsters and the Longshoremen's Unions. Moderator of the program is Ned Brooks, and the four questioning reporters are, left to right: Clark Mollenhof of the Des Moines Register and Tribune, May Craig of the Portland, Maine Press-Herald, William Hines of the Washington Evening Star, and Lawrence Spivak.
    - Local 100 Food Baskets, circa 1950s (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0846)
      Transport Workers Union Local 100 party.
    - Local 100 Leaflet Distribution, circa 1950s (Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0856)
      See the video reproduction cuid36995 in Subseries I.B.
      Leaflet distribution; Michael Quill at press conference.
    - Local 100 NYC Mack School, circa 1950s (Film canister c127, 16mm film reels 001_0273)
      A technician demonstrates or instructs a group of men on the features of a Mack diesel engine.
    - Mass Meeting, circa 1950s (Film canister c119, 16mm film reels 001_0245)
      Transport Workers Union officers and members seated and standing around a long table.
    - Michael Quill Announces End of Strike, circa 1950s (Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0845)
      Transport Workers Union's Michael Quill announces end of a strike by Philadelphia TWU workers.
    - Michael Quill Press Conference, circa 1950s (Film canister c159, 16mm film reels 001_0189, 001_0190, 001_0191)
      Two outtakes from Michael Quill press conference. He reports that leaders of Transport Workers Union met with Gerald O'Casey and the Transit Authority to present their $50 million proposal and demands for exclusive bargaining rights, and announces Transport Workers Union's intention to continue collective bargaining per the memorandum of understanding with the city until December 15.
    - Miscellaneous Trims, circa 1950s (Box 29, 35mm film reels 001_0432)
      Miscellaneous trims, almost all from scenes present elsewhere in the collection.
    - Our Case for the Forty Hour Work Week, 1950 (Film canister c8, 16mm film reels 001_0792)
      See the video reproduction cuid36984 in Subseries I.B.
      Consists of scenes from demonstrations, meetings, a television program and press conference from the Transport Workers Union's drive to win a forty-hour week for New York City Board of Transportation employees. Narration is provided by printed titles.
    - Outtakes, Transit Authority Reports, circa 1950s (Film canister c113, 16mm film reels 001_0280)
      Several takes each of a New York City Transit Authority official and a representative of privately-owned bus companies in New York City reporting on a luncheon hosted by the companies and the Transport Workers Union for representatives of the newly (re-?) constituted Transit Authority to discuss common problems and how to increase ridership on mass transportation in New York City; Flubbed takes of another New York City official giving a report on illegal parking from 14th Street to 60th Street.
    - Picket Line, Mass Rally, circa 1950s (Box 26, 16mm film reels 001_0851)
      Transport Workers Union picket line; Transport Workers Union leaders address mass rally.
    - Powerhouse Footage, circa 1950s
      - Film (Box 17, Film canister c111, 16mm film reels 001_0371)
        Shots of exteriors, interiors, and operations at a powerhouse.
      - Film (Film canister c82, 35mm film reels 001_0223)
        See the video reproduction cuid37011 in Subseries I.B.
        Exterior shots of a New York City powerhouse facility.
      - Film (Film canister c79, 35mm film reels 001_0318)
        Interior shots of a New York City powerhouse facility.
      - Film (Box 19, Film canister c83, 35mm film reels 001_0417)
      - Film (Box 17, Film canister c111, 16mm film reels 001_0370)
        This film exhibits symptoms of severe vinegar syndrome.
    - Press Conference, circa 1950s (Box 30, 16mm film reels 001_0301)
      Michael Quill seated between two groups of men looking over a contract or agreement, possibly in the midst of negotiating.
    - Press Conference on NYCTA Agreement, circa 1950s (Film canister c113, 16mm film reels 001_0281)
      Press conference by Transport Workers Union's Michael Quill. He announces the conclusion of an agreement between the Transport Workers Union and the New York City Transit Authority for its 37,000 employees.
    - Press Conference with the International Executive Board, circa 1950s (Box 30, 16mm film reels 001_0300)
      Press conference in which Michael Quill announces that the International Executive Board of Transport Workers Union recommends to Transport Workers Union Local 100 that it prevent, by any means, proposed layoffs being prepared by the Board of Transportation and the proposed new Transit Authority. The Union's demands included immediate collective bargaining, a wage increase of 25 cents per hour, and a contract that includes provisions making Transport Workers Union the sole collective bargaining agent for all employees of the Board of Transportation.
    - Press Conferences with Michael Quill, 20th Anniversary Meeting, circa 1950s (Box 23, 16mm film reels 001_0830)
      See the video reproduction cuid36992 in Subseries I.B.
      Two press conferences with Michael Quill speaking; passengers on New York City subway trains and buses; Transport Workers Union's 20th anniversary meeting.
    - Press Conferences with Michael Quill, circa 1950s (Box 21, 16mm film reels 001_0853)
      Various press conferences held by Michael Quill and other leaders of the Transport Workers Union; Transport Workers Union rallies and meetings; interview with Senator Wayne Morse.
    - Santa Claus Promotes Public Transportation, circa 1950s (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0848)
    - Storm Meeting, 153 West 64th Street NYC, circa 1950s (Box 16, Film canister c128, 16mm film reels 001_0387)
      Workers disentangling telephone wires from and cutting down a fallen tree in front of a house; group of hunters walking up snowy slope on an open landscape; brief shots of meeting of Transport Workers Union officers.
    - Street Endorsements for Mayor Wagner, circa 1950s (Film canister c159, 16mm film reels 001_0186)
      Outtakes of street interviews with workers endorsing Robert Wagner for mayor of New York.
    - William O'Dwyer Luncheon, circa 1950s (Film canister c92, 16mm film reels 001_0225)
    - Film Clips, circa 1950s-1960s (Film canister c3, 16mm film reels 001_0791)
      Clips from Twenty-Nine Days to Victory and The Nation's Future; Debate between Michael Quill and Fred Hartley Jr.
    - Local 100 Election, July 6, 1951 (Film canister c10, 16mm film reels 001_0793)
      Local 100 members of the Transport Workers Union voting in a union election or referendum.
    - Negotiations Between TWU and Private Bus Lines, circa 1951 (Film canister c11, 16mm film reels 001_0442)
      See the video reproduction cuid36986 in Subseries I.B.
      Amateur film on contract negotiations between Transport Workers Union and New York City private bus lines. Narration is supplied by printed titles.
    - Convention, 1952 (Box 27, 16mm film reels 001_0912)
      See the video reproduction cuid36987 in Subseries I.B.
      Speakers include Father Charles Owen Rice of Pittsburg, and Philadelphia's Mayor Clarke.
    - Philip Murray Memorial Clips, circa 1952 (Box 18, Film canister c176, 16mm film reels 001_0364)
      Selects from two films on Philip Murray: the CIO's Imprint of a Man--The Story of Philip Murray (1952) as well as a filmed report from the Philip Murray Memorial Foundation.
    - Philip Murray Speech, 1952 (Box 29, Film canister c163, 16mm film reels 001_0360)
      Part of the Philip Murray Memorial documentary that is unrelated to the rest of the roll; includes an address by Murray on the upcoming 1952 presidential election
    - Allan Haywood Clips, 1952-1953 (Film canister c167, 16mm film reels 001_0210)
      Various segments of Allan Haywood speaking.
    - Film Selects for Phil Murray Memorial, 1952-1957 (Film canister c134, 16mm film reels 001_0176)
      Selects from two films on Philip Murray: the CIO's Imprint of a Man--The Story of Philip Murray (1952) and the Transport Workers Union's A Memorial Tribute to Philip Murray (1957).
    - Mass Meeting on Strike Against Private Bus Lines, January 23, 1953 (Box 33, 16mm film reels 001_0302)
      Mass meeting of strikers on twenty-third day of the Transport Workers Union strike against New York City private bus lines. Speakers include Matthew Guinan, Morris Lushewitz, John O'Connell, John F. O'Donnell, and Ellis Van Riper.
    - Television Program on Transit Authority, October 7, 1953 (Box 29, 16mm film reels 001_0897)
      See the video reproduction cuid36991 in Subseries I.B.
      Television broadcast in which Transport Workers Union officers report to Local 100 members on relations with the Transit Authority and the Transport Workers Union's program for working conditions and wages on New York City subways and buses and in privately owned bus companies.
    - NYC CIO Council Endorsements, October 18, 1953 (Box 33, 16mm film reels 001_0231)
      New York City CIO Council endorses mayoral candidate Robert F. Wagner. Includes a campaign advertisement and statements by New York City union leaders and by Wagner himself
    - New Headquarters Commemoration, circa December, 1953 (Box 23, 16mm film reels 001_0817, 001_0818)
      See the video reproduction cuid1025 in Subseries I.B.
      At the last official meeting of the Transport Workers Union to be held in its old headquarters, the organization commemorates its history and salutes the opening of its new headquarters.
    - Memorial Tribute To Mr. CIO -- Allan S. Haywood, 1953
      Compilation documentary featuring photographs and moving images of Allan Haywood intercut with music and narration eulogizing Haywood and reviewing his biography.
      - Film (Film canister c23, 16mm film reels 001_0808)
      - Film (Film canister c113, 16mm film reels 001_0283)
      - Film (Box 19, Film canister c114, 16mm film reels 001_0427)
      - Edited silent cut (Film canister c109, 16mm film reels 001_0321)
    - Private Bus Lines Strike, 1953
      - Film (Box 18, Film canister c164, 16mm film reels 001_0361)
        Michael Quill speaks to strikers at Transport Workers Union's 1953 New York City private bus lines strike.
      - Film (Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0440)
        See the video reproduction cuid1026 in Subseries I.B.
        Michael Quill attempts to bring a Transport Workers Union meeting to order.
      - Film (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0806)
        See the video reproduction cuid36990 in Subseries I.B.
        Includes shots of TWU strike against private bus lines, and shots of subway stations.
      - Film (Box 17, Film canister c7, 16mm film reels 001_0376)
        Demonstrations, picket lines, rallies of Transport Workers Union urging New York City's Board of Transportation to practice collective bargaining.
      - Clips, 1953 (Film canister c137, 16mm film reels 001_0299)
        Clips from the Transport Workers Union's 1953 strike against New York City private bus lines.
    - Bus Strike -- Mass Meetings, 1953
      Includes footage from mass meetings of strikers during the Transport Workers Union Local 100's strike against private bus lines in New York City.
      - Film (Film canister c141, 16mm film reels 001_0264)
        Includes a CIO official addressing a mass meeting of strikers.
      - Film (Film canister c170, 16mm film reels 001_0197)
      - Film (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0807, Box 21, 16mm film reels 001_0811)
      - Film (Film canister c20, 16mm film reels 001_0809)
        See the video reproduction cuid36989 in Subseries I.B.
        Michael Quill addresses mass meeting of strikers.
      - Film (Box 27, 16mm film reels 001_0433)
        Michael Quill addressing two different mass meetings.
      - Film (Film canister c141, 16mm film reels 001_0259)
        Shots of the audience at a mass strike meeting.
      - Film (Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0296, Box 32, 16mm film reels 001_0297)
        Various shots of audience and speakers at a mass strike meeting.
      - Film (Box 31, 16mm film reels 001_0916)
        See the video reproduction cuid36988 in Subseries I.B.
        Michael Quill and Matthew Guinan at a mass meeting on the eve of a private bus lines strike in New York City.
      - Film (Film canister c116, 16mm film reels 001_0342)
        Michael Quill addresses a mass strike meeting.
      - Outtakes (Box 19, Film canister c108, 16mm film reels 001_0411)
        Outtakes, audience shots, and speech from strike meeting.
    - Bus Strike -- Father Charles Owens Rice Speaks, 1953 (Box 32, 16mm film reels 001_0914)
      Father Charles Owen Rice making a statement of support for a Transport Workers Union strike.
    - Bus Strike -- Father Charles Owens Rice Statement, Strike Clips, 1953 (Box 32, 16mm film reels 001_0294)
      Father Charles Owen Rice gives a statement of support for Transport Workers Union's strike; demonstration in same strike; people crowding onto subway trains.
    - Bus Strike -- Line Reports, 1953 (Box 25, 16mm film reels 001_0436)
      Officers of the Transport Workers Union report on the progress of the 1953 New York City private bus lines strike.
    - Bus Strike -- Gustav Faber Speaks, 1953 (Film canister c141, 16mm film reels 001_0262)
      Gustav Faber speaking at mass meeting of Transport Workers Union strikers during TWU's 1953 strike against New York City private bus lines.
    - Bus Strike -- Michael Quill Interview, 1953 (Film canister c89, 16mm film reels 001_0234)
      Broadcast focusing on the strike in progress by the TWU against New York City's private bus lines; includes interview with the union's leader, Michael Quill.
    - Bus Strike -- Philadelphia Support, 1953 (Film canister c141, 16mm film reels 001_0260)
      Expressions of support for Transport Workers Union's 1953 strike against New York City private bus lines by leaders of Transport Workers Union's Philadelphia Local.
    - Bus Strike -- Press Conference, 1953 (Film canister c141, 16mm film reels 001_0263)
      Michael Quill press conference on Transport Workers Union's 1953 New York City bus strike.
    - Bus Strike -- Press Release, 1953 (Film canister c141, 16mm film reels 001_0261)
      Press release by Michael Quill regarding the TWU bus strike. Ellis Van Riper, John O'Donnell, Matthew Guinan, and Gustav Faber are also present.
    - Bus Strike -- Press Release with Outtakes, 1953 (Box 28, 16mm film reels 001_0915)
      Several takes of filmed press release by Transport Workers Union; includes Michael Quill speaking.
    - Election Footage, circa 1953 (Box 24, 16mm film reels 001_0441)
      Transport Workers Union members voting in a Transport Workers Union election or on contract or strike settlement.
    - Mass Meeting, 1953 (Film canister c119, 16mm film reels 001_0246)
      Matthew Guinan reads aloud a resolution to mass strike meeting.
    - Mass Meeting, 1953 (Film canister c119, 16mm film reels 001_0244)
      Speakers at Transport Workers Union mass meeting.
    - Mass Meeting, Michael Quill Address, 1953 (Film canister c159, 16mm film reels 001_0185)
      Trims, including audience shots at mass meeting, Michael Quill press conference, Transport Workers Union members voting
    - Mass Meeting, Michael Quill Interview, Press Conference, 1953 (Film canister c159, 16mm film reels 001_0187)
      1) Transport Workers Union mass meeting; 2) Michael Quill, flanked by Guinan, is interviewed by a reporter at the very beginning of the 1953 strike against New York City private bus lines; 3) Filmed press conference with Michael Quill.
    - NYC CIO Council Endorsements, 1953 (Film canister c90, 16mm film reels 001_0232)
      A campaign statement from New York City CIO council president, Michael Quill, replying to charges against Quill by the Republican candidate for mayor of New York and endorsing Democratic mayoral candidate Robert F. Wagner, Jr.
    - Phil Murray Memorial, Allan Haywood Memorial, 1953 (Film canister c110, 16mm film reels 001_0352)
    - Press Release on Subway Ridership, 1953 (Film canister c119, 16mm film reels 001_0247)
      Transport Workers Union's Michael Quill announces TWU's appeal to New York City's superintendent of schools to close schools for duration of strike.
    - Twenty-Nine Days to Victory, 1953
      A documentary that chronicles the 1953 strike of the Transport Workers Union Local 100 against nine privately owned New York City bus lines. It was produced shortly after the events it recounts.
      - Complete film (Box 34, 16mm film reels 001_0289, Box 17, Film canister c14, 16mm film reels 001_0381)
      - Edited sequences (Box 33, 16mm film reels 001_0290)
        Edited sequences without voiceover and music, including part of NYC CIO Council memorial meeting for Philip Murray.
      - Incomplete cut (Box 23, 16mm film reels 001_0292)
        Most of this footage comes from the second half of the film. Voiceover and music are missing.
      - Headline trims (Film canister c159, 16mm film reels 001_0188)
      - Outtakes (Film canister c157, 16mm film reels 001_0343)
        Matthew Guinan and Ellis Van Riper speak at mass meeting.
      - Outtakes (Box 29, 16mm film reels 001_0913)
        Rank and file members of Transport Workers Union at a union meeting; Allan Haywood and Michael Quill addressing mass meetings; workers going on and coming off shifts and at work.
      - Outtakes (Box 20, 16mm film reels 001_0869)
        See the video reproduction cuid1027 in Subseries I.B.
        Outtakes from a press conference in which Michael Quill reacts to an indictment that appears to have been handed down against either the Transport Workers Union or Quill himself by a Brooklyn grand jury.
      - Outtakes (Box 25, 16mm film reels 001_0214)
        Outtakes and trims of press conferences and leaders addressing meeting(s) during Transport Workers Union's strike.
      - Outtakes (Box 19, Film canister c112, 16mm film reels 001_0421)